<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href='./jonson.css'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ulysses</title> 
            <title><hi rend="italic">James Joyce</hi></title>   
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Shakespeare and Company</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London, United Kingdom</pubPlace>
            <date>1922 CE</date>
            <authority/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Joyce, James. Ulysses: A Facsimile of the Manuscript. Octogon Books, 1975.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc> 
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>
               <listWit>
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Joyce, James. Ulysses: A Facsimile of the Manuscript. Octogon Books, 1975.</witness>
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Joyce, James. Ulysses: A Facsimile of the Manuscript: A Facsimile of the First Edition Published in Paris. Orchises, 1998.</witness>
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Joyce, James. Ulysses. Modern Library, 1948.</witness>
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Joyce, James. Ulysses: The Corrected Text. Edited by Gabler, Hans et al., 1st American ed., Random House, 1986.</witness>
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Joyce, James. Ulysses: Errata 1922-1937 (Telemachus). Edited by Rose, Danis, and O’Hanlon, John. James Joyce Digital Archive, https://jjda.ie/u/ulex/a/ad10.htm. 2018. Accessed 15 May 2025.</witness>
               </listWit>
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <head><hi rend="bold">Textural Introduction</hi></head>
         <p>Ulysses: Telemachus</p>
         <p>James Joyce</p>

         <p>Critically Editing the Uneditable</p>
         <p>Reading Joyce could be understood as a game of error (Conley 6). Joyce's works are error-prone, but said errors are still inherently part of the work; trying to remove them naturally leads to controversy and contension (Conely 16). 
            Errors change meaning of sentences, changing the literary analysis of said words, changing the common understanding of Joyce. Therefore, no critical understanding of Joyce is complete without understanding each and every error, and why to – or to not – correct them.</p>
         <p>Ulysses is no exception to this: from its first and rushed printing at Shakespeare and Company, to the Joyce wars between Gabler and Kidd, error has been ever-present. 
            It is the job of a critical editor to edit their edition such that error is minimized; and usually this is done to works without any living author, and potentially without even a complete manuscript. While Ulysses does have a complete manuscript, the existence of a manuscript is only one piece of the story. The rest of the story, for "Ulysses," is much more complex.</p>
         <pb n="ix"/>
         <p>Even before the first copies of Ulysses were printed, there was already error. Joyce's eyesight was decaying while he was writing his manuscripts (Ascaso and Velze). His writings were often hard to decipher due to this. Ulysses is also very long and complex, inherently making any form of editorial process difficult.
            In addition, Joyce rushed publication of the 1922 edition, preventing Shakespeare and Co. from fully editing his work (Rossman 98). Shakespeare and Co.'s attempts at correcting these errors throughout the 1920s never led to a fully 'fixed' work, while also adding more errors (Rossman 98). Samuel Roth's pirated edition of "Ulysses," while at first seemly insignificant in impact, would cause the 1934 Modern Library edition - the primary way to read Joyce in the US after its unbanning - to be corrupted for over 30 years (Gerber 163). Random House later tried to publish a corrected edition in 1961, but this edition, like the editions both before and after, also had multiple novel errors.</p>
         <p>Hans Gabler would try to perfect Ulysses in his 1984 edition, and it seemed like he succeeded. Using computers, a team of the top Joyce academics, and the backing of the Joyce estate, he tried to correct over 5,000 errors, building a perfect Ulysses for the late 20th century (Rossman 99). But he did not succeed in his goal. Gabler's work would initially recieve positive acclaim by most Joyce scholars, but said acclaim would turn negative over a few years (Rossman 98 - 99). John Kidd argued that Gabler's 5,000+ edits weren't needed, and were in fact damaging to Ulysses scholarship as a whole; many other editors, including some of the editors of Gabler's own edition, along with members of the upper eschalon of textural editing agreed that the Gabler edition was fundamentally flawed (Rossman 98 - 99). The debate would continue for several years, with its end not being caused by a better edition appearing, but by Joyce studies moving away from textural editing as a whole (Lernout 240).</p>
         <pb n="viii"/>
         <p>Many critical editions of Ulysses also forget the 'causal' reader of Joyce; said reader doesn't read critical editions with lots of editorial commentary, nor do they know much of Joyce scholarship – they read the book, probably with a textural companion like Don Gillford's "Ulysses Annotated" to understand the many oblique references Joyce writes about. There is no reason for a critical edition (like the Gabler's edition) to target this reader – but there is also no reason for that reader to not even understand the editorial process that Ulysses could fundamentally be argued as being.</p>
         <p>This edition's job isn't to try to reconstruct the platonic idea of a perfect Ulysses (as attempted with Gabler's edition); instead, its job is to allow the reader to understand the process of editing "Ulysses," and to hopefully give the reader that power. It also tries to collate not only the words of "Ulysses," but also some of the scholarly commentation of Ulysses – allowing the casual reader to understand Ulysses in more depth, but also with the ablity to chose which interpretation they want of Joyce.</p>
         
         <p>The Editorial Process</p>
         <p>Perfection isn't achievable, but building a better edition is. Unlike critical print editions (which usually use large amounts of footnotes or a very large appendix; Gabler's edition has over 200 pages of editorial commentary) or practically all digital editions (the digital Joyce Project, for example, practically prevents reading while having a note open), this edition uses a simple yet intutive interface – just click anywhere in the text to get a note about that text (click outside the text to remove the note). Using this better and digital interface allows notes to become considerably longer, but also less noticeable at first glance. One note can include all of the collations for a paragraph, a detailed reason for the editorial decision made for that paragraph, and the summary-collations for details given by the most commonly used textural companions.</p>
         <pb n="vii"/>
         <p>More specifically, each sentence edited from Joyce's manuscript is collated against 4 sources, though only two sources are generally used (the other two are non-authorial, and therefore are only shown for comparison). The first source is the first edition of Ulysses, published by Shakespeare and Company during 1922. As established eariler, this edition was rushed, and therefore had many errors. The second source is the James Joyce Digital Archive's '1922 - 1937' corrected manuscript/historical edition (also included in the James Joyce Archive), a historical reproduction of a British Libary manuscript authored by Joyce. However, outside of one area, this edition is very similar to the 1922 edition; additionally, since the editor hasn't seen the manuscript (due to temporal concerns with obtaining the James Joyce Archive), it is only collated against once.</p><p>A 1946 reprint of the 1934 Modern Library edition is used as an non-authorial collation, as the pre-1961 Modern Library editions were based on a pirated edition with many errors. 
            However, both the Joyce estate and James Joyce gave approval to the publication of this edition: a copyright notice by "Nora Joseph Joyce" can be seen at page vi, and a 1932 letter from James Joyce directly addressed to Random House (owners of Modern Library) co-founder Bennett Cerf is included within the introduction (xv - xvii). The last collated edition is the 1986 Gabler edition, a reading edition based on the Gabler 1984 critical edition; there are no major differences from the reading and critical editions outside of the obvious lack of editorial commentary and "a small number of minor amendments" (Gabler 650).</p>
         <pb n="vi"/>
         <p>After collating against the 4 other witness editions and manuscripts, an editorial decision is made: what should be on the actual page? This question is the question editors must answer everyday, and said answer should be always shown to the reader. This edition shows this answer to this important question in the notes (that show when you click a sentence or paragraph). Only when most, if not all editions and manuscripts agree on a sentence or paragraph is the answer not shown (because the sentence/paragraph must be editorially uncontroversial if there are no differences between any of the witnesses).</p>
         <p>For the critical notes, the process is slightly more complex. This edition uses 3 different textural companions commonly used with Ulysses; Don Gillford's Ulyssees Annotated, Blamires' New Bloomsday Book, and the digital Joyce Archive. Directly quoting each note almost certainly goes against both copyright and can't be done anyways, as Blamires' New Bloomsday Book isn't even based on annotations (instead, it is more like a long-form summary), unlike Ulysses Annotated or the Joyce Project. Instead, a summary comparing and contrasting all 3 sources (if avaliable) is used as the critical note. What's interesting is the contrast each companion has to reading the book – the critical notes, therefore, act as a way to show the many ways Ulysses can be interpreted, allowing the reader to come up with their own conclusions on Ulysses.</p>
         <pb n="iv"/>
         <p>There is no good choice for a copy-text while editing Ulysses; but this edition could be aruged to utilize the 1922 edition and 1917 manuscript as the copytexts. Later Shakespeare and Company edition, along with Odysses Press' 1932 edition are other authorially substantive and published editions of Ulysses (many manuscripts, letters, and other texts from Joyce also exist, along with probably other editions of Ulysses), but unfoutantly, those editions weren't used due to time constraints. This edition uses the same notation as the 1922 edition, excluding italization of dialog (due to software limitations).</p>
         <p>A Short Introduction to the Textural History of Ulysses</p>
         <p>The first known 'edition' of the first page of Ulysses (which is the edited page) is Joyce's 1917 manuscript. After conversations with periodicals (notably "The Little Review" published a early print of Telemachus) and publishers, by mid-1921 3 proofs were written by Joyce (see the James Joyce Digital Archive and the National Library of Ireland); however, the first page is remarkably identical across all 3 proofs and the inital manuscript, so none of these proofs were collated in the final edition.</p>
         <pb n="iii"/>
         <p>In 1922, Shakespeare and Company published the first edition of Ulysses; this edition was very rushed, and had a high number of errors (Rossman 99). Thoughout the 1920s, Shakespeare and Co. tried to correct their edition, but new errors were also introduced with their newer editions (Rossman 99). A pirated edition (by Samuel Roth) was published in the US during the mid-1920s (Kostelanetz). A multitude of errors have been found in that edition, and those errors later impacted the 1934 edition (Gerber 163). 
            The Odyssey Press' 1932 edition was edited by Stuart Gilbert, "at the author's request" (McCleery 90). The 1932 edition is probably based on a later Shakespeare and Co. edition, but the 1932 edition was generally thought to contain significantly less errors than prior (contemporary pre-Gabler) editions (McCleery 90).
            The Modern Library (or Random House) edition was the first American authorized edition of Ulysses, being published after the lift on the ban on Ulysses (Gerber 163). Unfortunately, it was based on the pirated 1929 edition, and it inherits the errors of that pirated edition (Gerber 163). The 1936 Bodley Head edition was the first edition published in the UK; it was also proofread by Joyce.</p>
         <pb n="ii"/>
         <p>In 1961, 2 decades after Joyce's death, a corrected Random House edition of Ulysses was published (Rossman 90). This edition would be the standard for Joyce scholarship until the Gabler edition. However, it still contained many errors (Rossman 90).
         The controversal Gabler edition was published in 1984, and after inital acclaim ('correcting' many errors), it was pulled from the shelves (Lernout 241). However, it is still often used for Joyce scholarship. 
         The Gabler edition was based on a genetic analysis of Joyce's writings (Rossman 98), with it probably being primarly based on Joyce's manuscript and proofs (generally, when collating, the Gabler edition has the most closest similarity with the manuscript). 
         A 'reader's edition' of Ulysses was published in 1997 by Danis Rose (Lernout 241).</p>
         <pb n="i"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Stately, plump Buck Mulligan came from the stairhead, leaving a bowl of lather on which a mirror and a razor lay crossed. 
            A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently behind him by the mild morning air. He held the bowl aloft and intoned: <note type="critical">Hunt's online Joyce Project directly states that Joyce is satirizing the Catholic mass; it notes that the 'yellow dressinggown' Mulligan is wearing is a symbol of heresy in Christanity, and his lack of girdling and torsored hair is symbolism for a lack of priestliness (Gillford argues similarly (13)). The Joyce Project also states that Buck Mulligan is based on Joyce's friend, Oliver Gogarty. Both Gillford's Ulysses Annotated and Blamires' New Bloomsday Book claim that that Buck Mulligan is satarically playing the role of a psalmist (more details on this with the notes on the second paragraph). Gillford believes that the razor symbolizes "the preist as butcher," while the Joyce Project argues that the mirror and razor "signal the tensions in the relationship between Mulligan and Stephen Dedalus."</note><note type="editorial">The removal of per-sentence notation makes the regular style of collation for this paragraph near-impossible to use. Therefore, only the changes will be noted.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: "A yellow dressing gown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1922 Ed.: "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: "STATELY, PLUMP [page break, large S covering almost the entire page] Buck Mulligan..." "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item></list></note></p>
            <p>– "Inliabo ad altare Dei." <note type="other">Translates to "I will go to the altar of God." A reference to Pslam 42, and used in Catholic masses.</note><note type="critical">Both Gillford's Ulysses Annotated and Blamires' New Bloomsday Book claim that that Buck Mulligan is satarically playing the role of a psalmist; Gilford aruges that Stephen Dedulus is also playing the role of a server (13), while Blamires just claims that Stephen Dedulus is playing the role of a visitor (3). The Joyce Project also implies that, but the commentary does not directly suggest this (click the first paragraph for more details).</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – inliabo ad altare Dei</item><item>1922 Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item></list></note></p>
            <p>Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called out coarsely: <note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called out coarsely:</item> <item>1922 Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item></list></note></p>
            <p>– "Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit." <note type="critical">Kinch is the nickname Mulligan has for Dedalus; both the Joyce Project and Ulysses Annotated (Gilford, 13) state that this was Oliver Gogarty's nickname for Joyce. The Joyce Project also speculates that 'kinch' could also be associated with other uses of knives throughout most of Telemachus. Gilford only gives a passing reference to the Jesuits as a intellectural "religous order of the Roman Catholic Church," (13) while the Joyce Project goes into much more detail, stating that Joyce had scholastic connections to the Jesuits, being taught at 2 Jesuit-associated schools during his youth.</note><note type="editorial">While the 1922 edition does capitalize "Jesuit," there is very good reason to believe that the capitalized "Jesuit" in the 1922 edition wasn't authorial - the manuscript and the James Joyce Digital Archives' intermediary proofs all have 'jesuit' in lower case. The Modern Library's edition's capitalization and punctionation is used here, as it seems to be the one which incorporates the most authorial intent over time (the exclaimation mark in the manuscript was corrected by Joyce in u1.3' (JJDA), and it was never seen in any other published edition (sanctioned by Joyce) since).</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – Come up Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit! </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful Jesuit. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit. </item><item>1937 (reconst. without errata JJDA) Ed.: – Come up, Kinch. Come up, you
               fearful jesuit. </item>
         <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Come up Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit! </item></list></note></p>
            <p>Solemnly he came forward and
            mounted the round gunrest. He faced
            about and stepped gravely thrice the tower,
            the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains, then, catching sight of
            Stephen Dedalus, he bent towards
            him and made crosses in the
            air, gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head. Stephen Dedalus, displeased 
            and sleepy, leaned his arms on the
            top of the staircase and looked coldly
            at the shaking gurgling face that
            blessed him, equine in its length
            and at the light untonsured hair
            grained and hued like pale oak. <note type="critical">The Joyce Project directly states that tower referenced is almost certainly based Joyce's experiences living on the tower at Sandycover Point (near Dublin) and that the 'awaking' mountains are the Wicklow Mountains (also near Dublin). It additionally states that Stephen Dedalus is based on James Joyce; his first novel, an bildungsroman titled "A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man," detailed the life of a 'Stephen Dedalus' that attended the same schools and had many of the same events as Joyce's own life. Gilford's Ulysses Annotated only states that 'gunrest' refers to "a raised circular patform" formerly used to hoist a gun at the tower (13); the Joyce Project additionally states that British military installations often had gunrests. Blamires' New Bloomsday Book does not discuss anything from here.</note><note type="editorial">The removal of per-sentence notation makes the regular style of collation for this paragraph near-impossible to use. Therefore, only the changes will be noted.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: "... the surrounding land and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his afm'd throat and shaking
            his head."</item> <item>1922 Ed.: "... the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: "... the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item><item>1984 (Gabler) Ed.: "... the surrounding land and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item></list></note></p>
            <p>Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly. <note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item> <item>1922 Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item>
            <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item></list></note></p>
            <p>– Back to barracks, he said sternaly. <note type="editorial">There is no real reason to think that Joyce would have not noticed the lack of 'the' in Mulligan's sppech and not do anything about it, 
            unless it was intentional; the much more incidential varience in the addition of a period in the 1922 edition shows that Joyce did (probably) check this sentence at least once – and also forgetting a period is just a common accident when writing manuscripts by hand (especially if your vision was severally degraded, as Joyce's was). I do not see any reason why Joyce's manuscripts, the 1922 edition, nor any Joyce-authored errata (at least incorporated in the Modern Library edition) would accidentally replace an exclaimation mark with a more-grammatical comma, nor why this was never corrected in later editions.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – Back to barracks he said sternaly </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – Back to barracks, he said sternaly. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Back to barracks, he said sternaly. </item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Back to barracks! he said sternaly. </item></list></note></p> 
            <p>He added in a preachy stance:</p>
            <p>– For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. <note type="critical">Both Gilford's Ulysses Annotated (14) and the Joyce Project state that the subsitution of 'Christ' or 'Christian' for 'Christine' is allusionary to the Black Mass, which is done over a woman's body.</note><note type="editorial">This is a (almost certainly) satire of Catholic masses; the usage of the 'corrupted' homophone "Christine" instead of "Christian" is a natural continuation of that satire (as argued in the critical note), and it shouldn't be edited out. The capitalization reflects real-world (as Christian is a proper noun) and parodic usage (generally speaking, people's names are capitalized), was never changed in any of the published editions during Joyce's lifetime, and could just easily be a mistake on the manuscript (again, Joyce had bad and worsening vision while writing Ulysses).</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            christine: body and soul and blood
            and oems. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpasoles. Silence, all. </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all.</item>
         <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: –For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            christine: body and soul and blood
            and oems. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. </item> </list></note></p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>THIS PAGE IS RESERVED FOR FUTURE USE</p>
         </body>
         <back>
            <p>Citations (witnesses and scholarly commentary):</p>
            <p>Ascaso, Francisco J., and Jan L. v. Velze. "Was James Joyce Myopic Or Hyperopic?" Bmj, vol. 343, no. 7837, 2011, pp. 1295-1295.</p><p>Blamires, Harry. The New Bloomsday Book: A Guide through Ulysses. 3rd ed, Routledge, 1996.</p>
               <p>Conley, Tim, and Project Muse. Joyces Mistakes: Problems of Intention, Irony, and Interpretation. University of Toronto Press, Buffalo, 2003.</p>
               <p>Gerber, Richard J. "Ulysses Arrives in the United States: A Perspective from Eighty Years Ago." James Joyce Quarterly, vol. 51, no. 1, 2013, pp. 163-167.</p>
Gifford, Don, and Robert J. Seidman. Ulysses Annotated: Notes for James Joyce’s Ulysses. 2nd ed., Univ. of California Press, 1988.

<p>Joyce, James. Ulysses: A Facsimile of the Manuscript: A Facsimile of the First Edition Published in Paris. Orchises, 1998.</p>

<p>---. Ulysses: A Facsimile of the Manuscript. Octogon Books, 1975.</p>

<p>---. Ulysses. Modern Library, 1948.</p>

<p>---. Ulysses: The Corrected Text. Edited by Gabler, Hans et al., 1st American ed., Random House, 1986.</p>

<p>---. Ulysses: Errata 1922-1937 (Telemachus). Edited by Rose, Danis, and O’Hanlon, John. James Joyce Digital Archive, https://jjda.ie/u/ulex/a/ad10.htm. 2018. Accessed 15 May 2025.</p>

<p>Kostelanetz, Richard. "Radical Publisher's Own Story Told." Forward, 25 Oct., 2013, pp. 26. ProQuest, https://proxy.wichita.edu/login?url=https://www.proquest.com/newspapers/radical-publishers-own-story-told/docview/1462205474/se-2.</p>
<p>Lernout, Geert. “Controversial Editions: Hans Walter Gabler’s Ulysses.” Text, vol. 16, 2006, pp. 229–41. JSTOR, http://www.jstor.org/stable/30227970. </p>
<p>McCleery, Alistair. "The Reputation of the 1932 Odyssey Press Edition of Ulysses." The Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America, vol. 100, no. 1, 2006, pp. 89-103.</p>
<p>Rossman, Charles. "introduction: A Special Issue on Editing Ulysses." Studies in the Novel, vol. 51, no. 1, 2019, pp. 98-103.</p>
         </back>
   </text>
</TEI>