<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href='./jonson.css'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ulysses</title> 
            <title><hi rend="italic">James Joyce</hi></title>   
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Shakespeare and Company</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London, United Kingdom</pubPlace>
            <date>1922 CE</date>
            <authority/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Ulysses manuscripts [add actual citation]</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc> 
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>
               <listWit>
                  
                  <witness xml:id="SIGLUM">Ulysses manuscript scans [add actual citation]</witness>
                  
               </listWit>
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Stately, plump Buck Mulligan came from the stairhead, leaving a bowl of lather on which a mirror and a razor lay crossed. 
            A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently behind him by the mild morning air. He held the bowl aloft and intoned: <note type="editorial">The removal of per-sentence notation makes the regular style of collation for this paragraph near-impossible to use. Therefore, only the changes will be noted.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: "A yellow dressing gown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1922 Ed.: "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: "STATELY, PLUMP [page break, large S covering almost the entire page] Buck Mulligan..." "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: "A yellow dressinggown, ungirdled, sustained gently..."</item></list></note></p>
         </p><p>– "Inliabo ad altare Dei." <note type="other">Translates to "I will go to the altar of God." A reference to Pslam 42, and used in Catholic masses.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – inliabo ad altare Dei</item><item>1922 Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Inliabo ad altare Dei. [italicized]</item></list></note></p>
            <p>Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called out coarsely: <note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called out coarsely:</item> <item>1922 Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: Halted, he peered down the dark
            winding stairs and called up coarsely:</item></list></note></p>
            <p>– "Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit." <note type="editorial">While the 1922 edition does capitalize "Jesuit," there is very good reason to believe that the capitalized "Jesuit" in the 1922 edition wasn't authorial - the Modern Library edition (which incorporated most of Joyce's own errata), the manuscript, and the James Joyce Digital Archives' reconstructions of intermediary proofs all have 'jesuit' in lower case. The Modern Library's edition's capitalization and punctionation is used here, as it seems to be the one which incorporates the most authorial intent over time (the exclaimation mark in the manuscript was corrected by Joyce in u1.3' (JJDA), and it was never seen in any other published edition (sanctioned by Joyce) since).</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – Come up Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit! </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful Jesuit. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Come up, Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit. </item>
         <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Come up Kinch! Come up, you
            fearful jesuit! </item></list></note></p>
            <p>Solemnly he came forward and
            mounted the round gunrest. He faced
            about and stepped gravely thrice the tower,
            the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains, then, catching sight of
            Stephen Dedalus, he bent towards
            him and made crosses in the
            air, gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head. Stephen Dedalus, displeased 
            and sleepy, leaned his arms on the
            top of the staircase and looked coldly
            at the shaking gurgling face that
            blessed him, equine in its length
            and at the light untonsured hair
            grained and hued like pale oak.<note type="editorial">The removal of per-sentence notation makes the regular style of collation for this paragraph near-impossible to use. Therefore, only the changes will be noted.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: "... the surrounding land and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his afm'd throat and shaking
            his head."</item> <item>1922 Ed.: "... the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: "... the surrounding country and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item><item>1984 (Gabler) Ed.: "... the surrounding land and the awaking
            mountains...," "...gurgling in his throat and shaking
            his head."</item></list></note></p>
            <p>Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly. <note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item> <item>1922 Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item>
            <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: Buck Mulligan peeped an
            instant under the mirror and then
            covered the bowl smartly.</item></list></note></p>
            <p>– Back to barracks, he said sternaly. <note type="editorial">There is no real reason to think that Joyce would have not noticed the lack of 'the' in Mulligan's sppech and not do anything about it, 
            unless it was intentional; the much more incidential varience in the addition of a period in the 1922 edition (and preservation in the Modern Library edition) shows that Joyce did (probably) check this sentence at least once – and also forgetting a period is just a common accident when writing manuscripts by hand (especially if your vision was severally degraded, as Joyce's was). I do not see any reason why Joyce's manuscripts, the 1922 edition, nor any Joyce-authored errata (at least incorporated in the Modern Library edition) would accidentally replace an exclaimation mark with a more-grammatical comma, nor why this was never corrected in those editions.</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – Back to barracks he said sternaly </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – Back to barracks, he said sternaly. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – Back to barracks, he said sternaly. </item><item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: – Back to barracks! he said sternaly. </item></list></note></p> 
            <p>He added in a preachy stance:</p>
            <p>– For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. <note type="editorial">This is a satire of Catholic masses; the usage of the 'corrupted' homophone "Christine" instead of "Christian" is a natural continuation of that satire, and it shouldn't be edited out. The capitalization reflects real-world usage of the non-parodic word, was never changed in any of the published editions during Joyce's lifetime, and could just easily be a mistake on the manuscript (again, Joyce had bad and worsening vision while writing Ulysses).</note><note type="collation"><list><item>1918 MS: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            christine: body and soul and blood
            and oems. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpasoles. Silence, all. </item> <item>1922 Ed.: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. </item><item>1934 (Modern Library) Ed.: – For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            Christine: body and soul and blood
            and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all.</item>
         <item>1986 (Gabler) Ed.: –For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine
            christine: body and soul and blood
            and oems. Slow music, please. Shut
            your eyes, gentlemen. One moment. A
            little trouble  about those white
            corpuscles. Silence, all. </item> </list></note></p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>THIS PAGE IS RESERVED FOR FUTURE USE</p>
         </body>
   </text>
</TEI>